Good morning.
早上好.
Yuli... Come on.
尤利...到你了.
Come on, bro!
到你了, 兄弟!
Go on, Yuli! Go on, Yuli!
上, 尤利! 上, 尤利!
You have to win, you have to win! Come on, come on!
你肯定会赢的, 你肯定会赢的!加油, 加油!
We're all ready.
我们都准备好了.
Are you?
你呢?
Right, I'm coming.
好, 我马上来.
Right, folks, change of order. We'll start the street scene.
好的, 伙计们, 下面我们来排街舞.
Let's move it...
动起来...
Yuli!
尤利!
Tina!
蒂娜!
-你看到尤利了吗? - What is it? - Have you seen Yuli?
-怎么啦?
No, no. I haven't seen him.
没, 没. 我没看到他.
Lads, have any of you seen my son?
小伙子, 你们有谁见到过我的儿子吗?
Damn it!
该死的!
Cundo, I've seen you around with Yuli. Do you know where he is?
昆豆, 我看见你和尤利在一起了. 你知道他在哪吗?
No.
我不知道.
- There we go. - Come on.
到我们了. 上!
Go on, Yuli.
上, 尤利.
He's winning!
他赢定了!
Hell! Let me through!
见鬼! 让我过去!
Hey, move over!
嘿, 滚开!
Get the hell up!
你给我起来!
Get off him! Shit!
让开! 该死的!
Come on, move it! When will you start behaving?
快起来! 什么时候才能干点正事?
Told you! I don't want you hanging around with these wasters.
跟你说过了, 不要跟这堆废物在一起!
It's sore!
很痛啊!
-你弄疼我了, 老爸! - You want to swing your arse? - You're hurting me, Papi!
-你喜欢扭屁股?
好, 你等着, 扭屁股... That's what you want, to strut your stuff? Well, you'll see, wriggle your arse...
这就是你想要的? 炫耀你那玩意?
Good night.
晚安.
Yuli, turn off the light.
尤利, 把灯关了.
Mami, where are we going?
妈咪, 我们这是去哪?
Ask your dad...
问你老爸...
-我们是来面试的. - Good morning. - We're here for the audition.
-早上好.
Boys, straighten the legs.
男孩们, 腿伸直.
Look at that, all bent! Come on! Stretch!
看, 都是弯的! 来! 绷直!
It should hurt, push till it hurts! Stretch!
一定会疼的, 压到疼为止! 绷直!
Look at the legs, bent again. Stretch!
看看你们的腿, 又弯了. 绷直!
Bend down, put your head to your knees.
弯下去, 头碰膝盖.
Right down.
再往下.
Let's go up.
把腿抬起来.
Higher, Julia, higher.
高一点, 尤利, 再高点.
That's it.
对了.
So you want to be a dancer, Carlos?
卡洛斯, 这么说你想做一个舞者喽?
No, I don't.
不, 我不想.
- Yes, he does. - No, I don't.
-对, 他想. -不, 我不想.
Yes, you do.
是的, 你想.
So what do you want to be?
那你想做什么?
A footballer, like Pele.
足球运动员, 像贝利那样.
I want to wear boots, not panty-tights like those faggots out there.
我想穿球鞋, 不想像外面那些基佬一样穿紧身裤袜.
Now for the last little test. Could you dance something for us,
最后一个小测试, 你可以随便跳点什么给我们看吗?
- anything you like? - No.
-任何你喜欢的? -不.
Dance.
跳.
No.
不.
If you don't, me and you will be dancing back at the house.
如果你现在不跳, 我就让你回去跳个够!
Listen...
听着...
This is one of the best ballet schools in the world.
这是全世界最好的芭蕾舞学校之一.
It's not months of discipline, years of sacrifice. It's a way of life.
不仅仅是成年累月的训练和牺牲, 这是一种生活方式.
Not a job, but a vocation.
既不是工作, 也不是度假.
Listen, this is how it is. We live so far out, in the outskirts.
是这样, 我们住在很远的郊外.
It takes three buses in, three buses back... Two hours each way.
要转三次巴士到这, 再转三次巴士回去...每趟都要花两个小时
He's still a child.
他还是个孩子.
Yes.
对.
I'm very sleepy in the mornings.
我每天早上都爬不起来.
I began work when I was 9 years old.
我九岁时就开始工作了.
I survived.
还不是好好的.
You can get up with me in the mornings at 5. That's it!
你可以早上5点和我一起起床. 就这样!
The whole family has to be united, totally committed to it.
一家人都得赞同, 并且全身心投入才行.
Mami and Papi are divorced.
妈妈和爸爸已经离婚了.
But we still live together.
但我们仍然住在一起.
Like cat and dog.
像猫和狗一样.
Carlos, most kids would give anything to get into this school.
卡洛斯, 孩子们为了进这所学校挤破了脑袋.
In no other place in the world would you receive ballet classes,
世界上没有其他任何一所学校能像我们这里一样,
schooling, all for free, even the food. It's a luxury.
提供免费的芭蕾教学, 免费的餐食. 全部免费, 这是非常难得的.
You have something special which most kids don't have,
你有一些特质, 是其他孩子所没有的.
buckets of natural talent from head to toe.
从头到脚都饱含天赋.
Let's do this.
我可以带你.
You head home, talk to your Mami and Papi,
你回去跟你的爸爸妈妈商量一下,
and think about it, calmly. Then we talk.
冷静地考虑一下. 然后我们再聊.
Will you do that for me?
这样行吗?
No.
不行.
Turn off the light, Yuli.
尤利, 把灯关了.
Papi, I don't want to be a dancer.
老爸, 我不想学芭蕾.
I want to be normal.
我想做个普通人.
Well, too bad, partner.
这太糟了, 伙计.
My friends will drop me, call me a faggot.
我的朋友们不会跟我玩了, 他们会叫我基佬.
Don't worry.
别担心.
The son of a tiger has the same stripes.
虎仔也是老虎, 他们有同样的斑纹.
If they call you a poof, drop your pants, show them your big dick like your Dad's
如果他们敢叫你基佬, 你就脱掉裤子让他们看看你的擎天柱.
and tell them to go fuck themselves!
然后让他们吃屎去吧!
You are Yuli, son of Ogun, a Warrior God.
你是尤利, 战神奥岗的儿子.
I gave him that nickname, not you!
我给他起的名字, 不是你!
Bullshit, Berta! You weren't even there.
别瞎说, 贝尔达! 你那时根本就不在那.
I named you after an Indian brave the day you were born. Yuli!
你出生那天我为你取的名字, 印第安勇士尤利!
And you're going to be the best ballet dancer in the world.
你将成为世界上最好的芭蕾舞者.
That's it!
就这么定了!
Now shut up and get to sleep, all of you.
现在闭上嘴, 都给我睡觉.
Carlos, I'll leave you this.
卡洛斯, 这个给你.
Thanks.
谢谢.
Can I?
我能看看吗?
Yes.
可以.
Your old man must have loved you to pieces.
你老爹一定爱你爱到骨子里去了.
In his own way.
用他自己的方式.
On his own terms.
在他的世界里.
One, two, push to the floor, three,
一, 二, 下蹲, 三,
four, stretch.
四, 伸直.
Six, seven,
六, 七,
eight... And one,
八...再来, 一.
two,
二,
three... Chin up!
三...抬下巴!
Four,
四,
five,
五,
six, seven...
六, 七...
Carlos, please.
卡洛斯, 注意.
And one, two, three, four,
再来, 一, 二, 三, 四.
five, six, seven, eight. Tummies in!
五, 六, 七, 八. 收腹!
Ah, Mami! Is she coming or not?
妈妈, 她还来不来?
Ah, God, you are all so impatient! She said she was coming.
天啊, 你们为什么都这么急呢! 她说她已经在路上了.
You've been saying that for over half an hour!
你半小时前就说过这句话了!
Do you think we'll all fit in?
你觉得我们都坐得下吗?
They always take Berta.
他们总是带贝尔达.
You're a pain.
你好烦.
Listen, your aunt tries her best. That's enough.
听着, 你们的阿姨已经尽快赶来了. 别吵吵.
Children! No, no, no. Let's see how much space. Carlos!
孩子们! 不不不, 没位置了. 卡洛斯!
You two, out.
你们两出来.
But why?
为什么?
I can only take Berta.
我只能带贝尔达.
We're all squeezed up too tight.
车里太挤了.
Told you! You always bring her.
你为什么总是带她?
I'm really sorry...
很抱歉...
The next time we go to the beach, the first will be you two.
下次去海滩, 先带你们两.
Liar.
骗子.
Come here, darling...
过来, 亲爱的...
For God's sake...
看在上帝的份上...
Listen, love, we have to talk about something important, very important.
听着, 亲爱的, 我们得认真地谈谈.
- What happened? - No, don't worry. We'll talk.
- 发生了什么事? - 不用担心. 找个时间聊聊.
Don't worry.
不用担心.
Let's go.
我们走吧.
I spent the afternoon with my sister.
我跟我妹聊了一下午.
They're all leaving, fares paid, papers organized.
他们要走了. 账都结清了, 证件也备好了.
They'll make their way to Venezuela, then to Miami.
他们先去委内瑞拉, 然后再到迈阿密.
Perfect place for her.
很合适她的地方.
But she's taking Mum with her, Pedro.
但她要把老妈也带去, 佩德罗.
They...
她们...
Mireya wants to...
米雷娅想要...
bring me and Berta with them too,
把我和贝尔达也一起带去.
and leave Marilin and Carlos here with you.
让玛瑞琳和卡洛斯留下来陪你.
What?
啥?
What are you saying?
你说什么?
Pedro, if I stay, I'll never see my mother again.
佩德罗, 如果我留下, 我就再也见不到我妈了.
So what are you going to do? Yuli and Marilin are your children too!
那你打算怎么办? 尤利和玛瑞琳也是你的孩子.
Papi, is Mami going to leave us?
爸比, 妈咪要离开我们了吗?
Sleep, Yuli, sleep.
睡吧. 尤利. 睡吧.
It's very late, son.
很晚了, 儿子.
Tell me if she is going to leave us?
告诉我, 妈妈是不是要离开我们了?
Now, faster!
现在, 加速!
Do you hear me?
听见了吗?
Watch where you're going! Pay attention, in front of you, son! Watch! Watch!
盯着你要去的方向! 注意正前方, 儿子! 小心! 小心!
Are you drunk or something?
你是喝醉了吗还是怎么了?
Papi! We're going to crash!
老爸! 我们要撞车了!
Acosta.
阿科斯塔.
Is it our surname?
这是我们的姓吗?
Do you see that bell up there?
你看到那上面的钟了吗?
It dictated everything here in the plantation.
它决定了这个种植园的一切.
The Acosta plantation.
阿科斯塔种植园.
If a slave ran off, they hunted him down with dogs.
如果一个奴隶逃跑了, 他们会带着狗追他.
An ounce of gold for each slave captured and returned.
每抓回来一个奴隶奖励一盎司黄金.
They prized strong black slaves like your great grandpa.
象你祖爷爷那样强壮的黑奴特别值钱.
They forced them to have sex with healthy women.
他们被强迫跟健康的女人交配.
Bred us like animals for gain.
为了赚钱把我们当牲口喂养.
They lived in barracoons, eaten away by fleas,
他们住在巴拉坑里, 跟跳蚤为伍,
one door to lock them in,
被一扇大门锁住,
one window for air...
只有一个窗户透气...
They even whipped pregnant women,
他们甚至还在地上挖了个坑,
laid them down over a scooped out hole to protect their bellies.
以方便抽打怀孕的女人.
The cruelest treatment were the stocks.
最残忍的是木枷.
Thick planks with holes. They would stick their head,
用一块掏了个洞的厚木板, 把头卡在里面,
arms and feet through the planks
手和脚也套在木板上,
and leave them there for months on end.
留在野外好几个月让他们自生自灭.
How do you know all this, Papi?
你怎么知道这些的, 老爸?
My mother, your grandmother, was born to a slave on this plantation.
我的妈妈, 就是你的奶奶, 就是出生在这个种植园里的奴隶.
350 years of slavery runs through our veins.
三百五十年来我们的血管里一直流淌着奴隶的血液.
It leaves its mark.
它在我们的思想和我们的心灵,
In our heads, in our hearts...
都留下了深刻的烙印...
Including the name.
包括我们的名字.
Acosta.
阿科斯塔.
Still dividing families to this day.
直到今天还在分裂着我们的家庭.
Like me and my half-sister Berta.
像我我同母异父的姐姐贝尔达.
They want to bring her to Miami because she's white.
他们要带她去迈阿密, 因为她是白人.
But we survived, son.
但是就算这样,
Even in these places
我们也顽强地生存下来了, 孩子.
we sang, danced, resisted, kept our Gods.
我们唱歌, 跳舞, 抵抗, 坚持我们的信仰.
We remember to make us stronger, more determined, hard as nails...
我们牢记要锻炼身体,让自己更强大, 更果断, 更敏锐...
We were, and we are, warriors.
我们过去是勇士, 现在也是.
Sons of Ogun! Yuli.
我们是奥岗的儿子! 尤利.
That's what we are. Warriors.
我们生来就是勇士.
You are beautiful, my son, inside and out.
我的孩子, 你从内到外都光彩夺目.
Nobody and nothing can hold you back. Ever.
没有任何人, 没有任何事能挡得住你, 永远没有.
Take it easy, guys, you are something else.
别紧张, 你们都是很特别的.
Carlos, this Acosta plantation, where is it?
卡洛斯, 这个阿科斯塔植物园在哪?
By Pinar del Rio, in San Juan y Martinez.
在马丁内斯的皮纳里奥.
But you know what? My father never brought me there.
但你们知道吗? 我父亲从来没带我去过那里.
You're joking!
不是吧!
Yes, it's all fiction.
是的, 都是虚构的.
It never happened. But it is all the truth.
我父亲没有带我回去过. 但我说的都是真的.
My grandmother was born to a slave on the Acosta plantation.
我的奶奶出生时就是阿科斯塔植物园里的一个奴隶.
As a kid I used to imagine my great Grandfather as a runaway slave,
我小时候经常幻想我的曾祖父是个逃跑的奴隶,
chased by the dogs,
被一群狗追着,
fighting the hunters, stuck in the stocks, being whipped, or worse.
和赏金猎人搏斗, 被木枷锁住, 被鞭子抽打, 或者更糟.
My father didn't know his own father,
我老爹不知道他老爹是谁.
his mother gave him many a beating, often cruel,
他老妈总是揍他, 发恨地揍他,
but if all this past and present was mixed up inside the head of my old man.
我老爹可能搞混了过去的这些事情,
Although it didn't happen this way,
虽然不一定像我说的这样,
the question is, does that mean it isn't the truth?
但谁又能说那就不是事实呢?
But, Carlos, are you going to tell us what is reality, and what isn't?
但是, 卡洛斯, 你会告诉我们哪些是真的吧?
Do you always know the difference?
你真的知道它们的区别吗?
If you are going to try and tell the story of your life, really go for it.
如果你想讲讲你的故事, 那就试试呗.
You have to go deep, where the big fish lie.
深入些, 有大料的那种.
Girls, a quick goodbye. Can't wait long.
姑娘们, 该道别了, 我们得走了.
Let's go, we could miss the plane.
我们走吧, 不然要赶不上飞机了.
If you change your mind, it's not too late.
如果你现在改变主意, 还来得及.
We can wait for you and Berta in Venezuela.
我们可以在委内瑞拉等你和贝尔达.
I can't.
我做不到...
OK, Maria, OK. That's it. Time.
好的, 玛丽亚, 好的, 那就这样. 没时间了.
- Don't forget me. - Promise me you'll take care of yourself.
- 不要忘记我. -答应我照顾好你自己.
Take care. Look after yourself. I'll never forget you, my love.
保重. 照顾好你自己. 我不会忘记你的, 亲爱的.
Ah, look at the fairy! Look!
看那个兔子! 看!
I hear you became a faggot!
我听说你变成基佬了!
Pansy boy!
娘娘腔!
Arms in position, legs stretched,
抬臂! 腿伸直.
lift the chin, shoulders down...
抬下巴, 放松肩膀...
Slowly, three, four... That's it!
慢下来, 三, 四...对了!
Five.
五.
Seven, eight...
七, 八...
Turn to the bar.
转向杆.
Four, don't hang on the bar.
四, 不要靠在杆上.
Carlos Acosta! Come back here immediately!
卡洛斯阿科斯塔! 给我回来!
Where's that kid going?
那个孩子要去哪?
Don't let him out!
不要让他出去!
Back from there. You're going to fall.
进来点. 你要掉下去了.
Yuli!
尤利!
All this was built on a private golf course.
这里最早是一个私人高尔夫球场.
Fidel and Che played the last game of golf here just after the revolution.
菲德尔和切格瓦拉在革命刚刚成功之后, 在这儿打过一场高尔夫球.
Fidel had the dream of transforming it
菲德尔曾经想过把这里
into the most spectacular City of the Arts in the world.
改造成世界上最华丽的艺术中心.
Music, dance...
音乐, 舞蹈...
And here we are in what was to be the ballet school...
我们现在所在的地方, 本来是打算作为芭蕾舞学校...
Follow me.
跟我来.
Garatti, the architect, was inspired by the spirit of the times,
建筑师格拉迪受时代思潮的影响,
by the revolution...
和革命的启发...
Multiple entrances and exits,
多重出入口.
open to possibility,
提供了流畅的空间,
flowing, sweeping and interconnected,
大规模的流动和集结,
bold and imaginative.
大胆自信, 充满想象力.
I was a volunteer student working here
我学生时期在这里做过志愿者,
till construction was cut short in '65, just a few weeks short of completion.
直到整个工程1965年被叫停, 还差几周就能完工.
Times changed.
时代变了.
We had the Bay of Pigs,
我们经历了猪湾事件,
sabotage, assassination attempts, the economic embargo, hardship...
颠覆, 刺杀, 经济封锁, 困难时期...
The Soviets moved in, political space shrank.
苏联人来了, 政治空间被压缩.
All this designated "non productive" by the Russian advisors
苏联顾问说这些项目是"小资情调",
and never used.
从未启用过.
It's so sad, one of the most inspiring buildings in the world falling to pieces.
太令人难受了, 世界上最激动人心的建筑之一就这么废弃了.
Is it possible to rebuild it?
有没有可能重建?
Hey, kid! What a fright you gave me! Who are you?
嘿, 小鬼! 你吓了我一跳! 你是谁?
Rambo.
兰博.
PRISON COMBINADO DEL ESTE
东方联合监狱
I'll get out soon, don't worry.
我很快就能出去, 不用担心.
It'll all work out fine.
事情会得到解决的.
How's your Mami?
你妈妈好吗?
Don't worry, Papi, we're taking good care of her.
别担心, 我们会照顾好她的.
Aren't we?
对吧?
- Yes. - Yes.
- 对. - 对
I'm so proud of you all.
我真为你们感到骄傲.
And you, Berta, how are you?
你呢? 贝尔达, 你还好吗?
Fine.
好.
- And you, Marilin? - Fine.
- 你呢? 玛瑞琳? - 好.
Fine, fine... Is that all you can tell me?
好, 好...你们就只能告诉我这些?
We had to sell the fridge.
我们不得不把冰箱给卖了.
What? The fridge?
啥? 冰箱?
Shit!
该死的!
Faggot!
基佬!
You bloody clown, go fuck yourself!
你这该死的乡巴佬, 滚回你的狗窝去吧!
Screw you!
去你的!
Carlos Acosta!
卡洛斯阿科斯塔!
The concert starts in 40 minutes!
音乐会还有40分钟就要开始了!
Look at yourself!
看看你是什么样子!
Move it!
走!
Open the door.
开门.
Look at your hands! Don't dare touch a thing. A mud bath!
看看你的手! 你敢碰个东西给我看看, 都是泥!
You're stinking, filthy!
你可臭死了, 太脏了!
You promised to come!
你答应要来的!
Are you not ashamed of yourself?
你不觉得羞愧吗?
Letting us down and your classmates.
抛下我们和你的同学们.
Let me see your face.
让我看看你的脸.
And your Dad? Just you wait!
你爸爸呢? 怎么就你一个!
When he finds out?!
他咋没出现?
We were calling his work. Nobody knew anything.
我们打电话到工地找他. 没人知道他在哪.
He's in prison.
他进监狱了.
- What? - What!
- 啥? -啥!
I'm up to here with your stories!
你别再编故事了!
Such a liar, you've missed half the classes
你个小骗子, 你旷了一半的课程.
and always ready with a new excuse!
还总能捏造出新的借口!
It's not a lie.
真没骗你们.
A motorbike crashed into the back of Papi's lorry.
一辆摩托车追尾了我爸的卡车.
The boy was killed, and they blamed Papi.
车手死了, 他们怪罪我老爸.
And your Mami?
你的妈妈呢?
And your Mami, Carlos?
你的妈妈呢, 卡洛斯!
She's ill.
她生病了.
I'm sorry, sweetheart, really sorry.
我很抱歉, 亲爱的, 真的很抱歉.
But you know what we can do now?
但是你知道我们现在应该做什么吗?
We can take a photo, eh?
我们可以拍张演出的照片, 不是吗?
You can show it to your parents and it'll cheer them up.
你可以拿去给父母看, 这能够鼓舞他们.
Look.
看.
You are going to look gorgeous.
穿上这个你会变得很漂亮.
I'll look like a faggot.
我会象个基佬才对.
Move it! Run!
快! 用跑的!
Come on, Carlos, run, you're so late!
快啊, 卡洛斯, 跑起来, 你已经迟到了!
At last! Here he is! Silence! Silence! In position!
他终于来了! 安静! 安静! 站好!
You're a disaster.
你可差点搞砸了.
And you stink!
你可真臭!
Holy shit, boy!
天啊, 小子!
Look at the way you hold yourself, that neck, the smile...
看看你摆的姿势, 看看这脖子, 这笑容...
Real talent, my God.
上帝啊, 你真是个天才.
Born to dance, son.
儿子, 你天生就是块跳舞的料.
I played the main role.
我演的是主角.
Tell me, are you going to your classes?
告诉我, 你去上课了吗?
Yes. Up at the crack of dawn.
当然. 天刚亮就起床...
Don't want to let you down.
我不想让你失望.
And I'm in the top 5 best students of the school.
而且我是学校里最好的五个学生之一.
You don't say... And are you on time?
你不是说...你有准时去上课吗?
Yes. They say it's the biggest turnaround in the history of the school.
有啊, 他们说这是学校见过最大的一次进步.
- Even the teachers can hardly believe it. - Yuli, are you telling me the truth?
- 连老师们都不敢相信. - 尤利, 你告诉我的是实话吗?
Yes.
是的.
Come here, son.
过来, 儿子.
Come here I said... Come.
我说过来...过来.
I'm so proud of you, my boy.
我为你骄傲, 我的孩子.
You're going to be great one day, son. Right up there, damn it.
总有一天你会在舞台上有所成就, 儿子. 总有一天.
The Gods answered my prayers.
众神回应了我的祈祷.
What a load of bullshit!
你都胡扯了些啥!
I was talking and talking and couldn't stop.
我说着说着就停不下来了.
I just tried to cheer him up.
我就想让他高兴高兴.
"Biggest turnaround"!
"最大的进步"!
When he gets out and learns the truth, he's going to kill you.
他出来后知道真相的话, 一定会杀了你的.
You're dead.
你死定了.
Come here!
过来!
There!
那!
Pedro!
佩德罗!
Leave him, Pedro!
放开他, 佩德罗!
- Pedro, please! - Papi, leave him!
- 别打了, 佩德罗! - 别打了, 爸爸!
Pedro, leave him! You're going to kill him.
佩德罗, 放开他! 你会打死他的.
Leave him!
放开他!
Pedro!
佩德罗!
You're killing my child...
你会把我的孩子打死的...
Stop it, Papi!
住手, 爸爸!
Open the door!
开门!
Open the door, for God's sake!
看在上帝的份上, 开门啊!
What did he do to you, love?
他对你都做了些啥呀?
It's OK.
没事了.
I'm here, my love.
我在这, 亲爱的.
My love...
我的宝贝...
It's OK, my love... OK.
没事了, 亲爱的...没事了.
Son of a bitch! I hate you!
狗娘养的! 我恨你!
Chery, this doesn't make sense for anyone.
切莉, 这对谁都不公平.
For the teachers, for the students, nor for him.
不管是对老师, 对其他学生, 或者对他自己.
Look, there is a serious problem of truancy and suspensions.
你看, 他有严重的旷课和挂科问题.
That's the problem, Carlos, you just don't want to dance.
卡洛斯, 问题在于你根本就不想跳舞.
- Yes, he does! - Let the boy answer for himself! Please!
- 不是, 他想. - 请让孩子自己回答!
This child was born to dance! He just doesn't know it yet!
这个孩子是块跳舞的料! 只是他还没有意识到这点!
Do you ever listen to your son?
你是否倾听过你儿子的意见?
You have to understand the family situation has been tough.
你得理解这个家庭的情况非常困难.
Pedro has just been released from prison
佩德罗刚刚从监狱里放出来,
and Carlos has been cared for by his two sisters,
而卡洛斯是由他的两个姐姐照顾的,
practically children themselves.
她们自己都还只是孩子.
I understand all that... My opinion is that we are just wasting time.
这我都能理解...我的意见是我们纯粹在浪费时间.
We won't cross paths with a boy like this again.
我们很难再碰到这么优秀的小男孩了.
Pedro, can you give us a few minutes, please, and wait outside?
佩德罗, 你能给我们几分钟时间吗? 请在外面等等?
For a man like me, this is very difficult...
作为一个男人很难开口...
I'm going to beg for the first and last time in my life.
我这辈子第一次也是唯一一次乞求你们,
I know what is inside him.
我知道他的才华.
I beg you to give this child one last chance.
我乞求你们给这个孩子最后一次机会.
Let's go.
走吧.
When I was 25
在我25岁那年,
one day I sneaked into the cinema.
有一天我溜进了电影院.
On a big silver screen...
在一块巨大的银幕上...
there were delicate figures like parasols up there...
有几个精美的身姿如阳伞般婷婷玉立...
Suddenly they made mighty leaps,
突然他们做了几个大跳,
full of strength...
充满力量...
It all got me, deep inside.
它深深地打动了我.
I didn't know what it was.
我不知道那是什么.
I forgot my work and my shitty life.
但我彻底忘记了我的工作和糟糕的处境.
I felt it here, in my chest, as if it was part of me.
我的心灵感受到冲击, 就好象它是我的一部分.
The police arrived,
警察来了,
they dragged me out and gave a beating.
他们把我拖出去并给了我一顿胖揍.
Blacks couldn't go to the cinema.
黑人是不被允许进电影院的.
I fought back and they beat me with their truncheons.
我还手, 他们就用警棍打我.
Yuli,
尤利,
I would prefer to take a beating every day for the rest of my life...
我宁可余生中每天都挨一顿打,
than see you waste your talent.
也不愿意看到你浪费你的天赋.
There's no sense in him staying here.
我们没有理由让他继续留在这里.
But there is one last chance to continue dancing.
但还有最后一个机会让他能够继续学习舞蹈.
An ESBEC.
一个ESBEC名额.
What's that?
什么?
A boarding school in the countryside.
郊外的一家寄宿学校.
Pinar del Rio.
比纳尔得里奥.
Drag me from home? No, Papi! Tell her no!
寄宿? 不要, 老爸, 告诉她不要!
I've got a home... I want to stay here.
我有个家...我想呆在这里.
Carlos, this is your last chance.
卡洛斯, 这是你最后的机会.
No! No, Papi! Tell her no!
不要! 不要, 老爸! 告诉她不要!
Most of us, son, are "stuck".
孩子, 我们多数人都"定型"了.
Not you...
但你不是...
Tell her no!
告诉她不要!
You have a star to follow.
你有一条星路可以追随.
Carlos, they'll treat you well.
卡洛斯, 他们会好好待你的.
Papi, tell her no! Please!
老爸, 告诉她不要! 求你了!
Chery, thank you.
切莉, 谢谢你.
I'll never forget what you are doing for my son.
我不会忘记你为我儿子作出的努力.
Mario, this part...
马里奥, 这部分...
I want you to open up. Understand?
我希望你放开些, 明白吗?
Really go for it, raw, hard... really hurts inside, get me?
真打, 使劲打, 打疼自己...痛彻心扉, 明白吗?
Pain... loneliness...
痛苦...孤独...
Do you know how I put it?
你知道我把它叫做什么吗?
"That Wednesday feeling".
"星期三情绪".
Wednesday was the only day families could visit their kids.
星期三是每周唯一一个家庭探望日.
But my father was always away in his lorry, my mother was ill...
但我的父亲总是忙他的工作, 而我的母亲病了...
I felt so alone in the enormity of it all.
在其他人团聚的热闹氛围下我觉得特别孤独.
It's a loneliness I've felt all my life,
我一辈子都记得那种孤独的感觉,
even today as a man, it's inside.
它深植在我的心底.
Loneliness never really leaves you.
从来没有真正离开过.
Acosta! Acosta!
阿科斯塔! 阿科斯塔!
That's mine!
那是我的!
What are you doing snooping in my locker? Acosta!
阿科斯塔, 你在我柜子里翻啥呢?
Silence, please, silence.
安静! 请安静.
This morning, as a priority, we are going to deal with a serious situation.
今天早上, 我们先来处理一件严重的事情.
A number of students have been witnesses and denounced the incident.
有几位同学见证并揭发了这一事件.
But we are going to listen to the pioneer who has something to say. OK?
但是让我们来听听当事人有什么要说的, 好吗?
Carlos Acosta, we are all waiting for you.
卡洛斯阿科斯塔, 我们在等你.
Tell your classmates. What are you?
告诉你的同学, 你是什么样的人?
You're a thief!
你是个小偷!
- And you're filthy! - And stink too!
- 你很肮脏! 还很臭!
Lausanne
瑞士洛桑
Come on... Give it to them.
加油...让他们看看你的本事.
Look at that!
看哪!
Look at his face.
看看他的脸.
Fuck! Fuck! Always at the key moment...
该死的! 该死的! 总是在关键的时候掉链子.
Fucking piece of shit!
该死的垃圾!
So many of them...
这么多人...
He's going to win...
- 他要赢了...- 是啊...- 他要赢了...
Quiet! Damn it!
安静! 别吵!
Look!
看!
He's done it!
他赢了!
I told you! I told you!
我说了吧! 我就说嘛!
We've got to celebrate!
我们得好好庆祝一下!
Yuli's won the World Cup!
尤利赢得了世界杯!
Your son... Your son... He cracked it.
你的儿子...你的儿子...他成功了.
It's about Yuli, Berta, he won a really important prize in Switzerland.
是尤利, 贝尔达. 他在瑞士得了一个真正的大奖.
Do you understand?
你能听懂吗?
This is like the first black man on the moon!
这就像第一个登上月球的黑人!
There were about 500 competitors!
有500个竞争者!
But when the black boy appeared... He nailed it! Game over!
当那个黑人男孩出现的时候...他赢了! 游戏结束了!
Yuli!
尤利!
That's great, Mami.
太棒了, 妈咪.
He'll spend his life far away from us now.
现在他将远离我们过他自己的人生.
Just like Mami.
就象你外婆一样.
Very good, Carlos, much better.
很好, 卡洛斯, 更好些了.
But remember in the second part, with more power, more.
但记住第二部分多点力量, 更有力些.
OK, now the duo.
好, 现在练双人舞.
Isabelle, come on.
伊莎贝拉, 来.
Thank you, teacher.
谢谢你, 老师.
"GOLDEN MULATO WINS SCHOLARSHIP IN TURIN"
"混血儿赢得图灵金奖"
Come on, Pedro, we're about to finish.
快点, 佩德罗, 我们快搬完了.
How are you all doing?
你们好吗?
How are you?
你好吗?
Are we going?
我们走吧?
I wish Papi and Mami could see this.
我希望爸爸和妈妈能看到这些.
My sisters, my friends, everybody...
我的姐姐, 我的朋友们, 每个人...
How did all this happen, teacher?
我们是怎么做到的, 老师?
The public...
观众...
Every seat full...
爆满...
Eyes fixed on you...
每双眼睛都注视着你...
Moments of wonder that will stick in their memories for ever...
那些令人惊叹的时刻将永远留存在他们的记忆里...
The music, colour,
音乐, 色彩,
light, youth,
光线, 活力,
beauty...
美好...
A privilege to have this life, Carlos.
没几个人能够拥有这样的荣光, 卡洛斯.
You can become a great dancer.
你能成为一个伟大的舞者.
I know that... but the question is, can you become a great artist?
我知道这点...但问题是...你能成为一个伟大的艺术家吗?
Teacher, I'm working as hard as I can.
老师, 我已经尽我所能地努力了.
I don't mean that.
我不是那个意思.
It's what you carry inside.
这关乎你代入的情绪.
Who you are.
你是谁.
How deep you're prepared to go inside yourself...
你准备多大程度地挖掘你的内心...
And the courage you have.
还有你的勇气.
- Bye. See you tomorrow. - Bye. See you tomorrow.
- 拜, 明天见. - 拜. 明天见.
One last thing before we leave... London.
最后还有件事...伦敦.
London? What about London?
伦敦? 伦敦怎么了?
The English National Ballet has offered you a contract.
英国国家芭蕾舞团提供了一份合约.
What?
啥?
A contract in London?
一份伦敦的合约?
Yes.
是的.
They have the best schools, the best dancers, the best teachers...
他们有最好的学校, 最好的舞者, 最好的老师...
Thank you.
谢谢.
No, teacher, I didn't mean that.
不是, 老师, 我不是那个意思.
I don't think I'm good enough...
我觉得我不够优秀...
Carlos...
卡洛斯...
Talent, intelligence, and determination... you can't buy them.
天赋, 智慧, 决断...这是买不到的.
They are free, darling.
与生俱来的.
Mami says you are to come quick.
妈咪说让你赶快过去.
- Yuli is on the phone. - What's wrong?
- 尤利打电话来了. - 什么事?
Don't know.
不知道.
What can I do in England with no English?
我不会英语在英格兰能干嘛呢?
Dancing, eating, fucking, you don't need grammar for all that!
跳舞, 吃饭, 爱爱, 这些都不需要通过语言交流!
What happened? What's he saying?
怎么了? 他说啥?
They want him as a Principal Dancer at the English National Ballet in London.
他们要他到伦敦英国国家芭蕾舞团去当首席舞者.
And the bloody clown wants to come back home.
而这个龟孙子想要回来.
Papi, you don't know how the Cuban National Ballet could react.
老爸, 你不知道古巴国家芭蕾舞团会如何反应.
Just in case you haven't looked in the mirror recently, you're black!
洒泡尿照照你自己, 你是黑人!
A chance of a lifetime!
人生的一次转机!
A black man seizes a prize like this in two hands,
一个黑人有这样的机会屈指可数,
and never lets go even if they try to kill him!
拼了命也不能让它溜走!
Papi, I'm going to miss you all so much.
老爸, 我不想离开你们.
No, Papi.
不, 老爸.
Shit! Forget about us, forget everything...
该死! 忘掉我们, 忘掉这边的一切...
Forget Cuba...
忘掉古巴...
No, Papi. You know I can't do that.
不, 老爸. 你知道我做不到.
The best way to help us is to move on.
帮助我们的最好方式就是朝前走.
Listen, one day this country will lay out the red carpet for you.
听着, 总有一天这个国家将会铺着红地毯迎接你的.
How's Berta?
贝尔达好吗?
Berta?
贝尔达?
Berta's fine.
贝尔达很好.
We're all fine, perfect, don't worry about us, son.
我们都很好, 非常好, 不用担心我们, 儿子.
Papi, you know I can't do that, don't ask me that.
老爸, 你知道我不能那么做. 不要再逼我了.
Do what you're told. Here's your Mami.
按照我说的做. 你妈妈要跟你说话.
When are you coming home, son?
儿子, 你什么时候回家?
Holy shit!
晕!
You accept the contract, accept the ticket.
接受合约, 收下机票.
But did you get permission from Cuba?
古巴政府批准了吗?
I've decided you go straight to London from Turin.
我已经决定了, 你从都灵直接飞去伦敦.
But, teacher, did you ask permission?
但是, 老师, 您寻求过批准了吗?
I'll sort it out when I get back. If you go back home...
我回去后会想办法解决的. 如果你现在回家...
They'll crucify you! No, no, no! Call you a traitor at the very least!
他们会惩罚您的! 不, 不, 不! 至少也是个叛徒的罪名!
No, no, I'm coming back with you.
不, 不, 我要跟您一起回去.
Andres Williams. You know who I'm talking about?
安德烈威廉斯. 你知道我说的是谁吗?
One of the greatest I ever saw...
我见过最好的舞者...
but black. No Romeo for him.
就因为他是黑人. 不能出演罗密欧.
You could be in a queue for a lifetime waiting your turn...
你回去可能一辈子也等不到出头的机会...
or you can break new ground.
你也可以现在就开辟新的天地.
Teacher, they could kick you of your job.
老师, 他们很可能免去你的职位.
Or even worse, cast aside.
或者更糟, 直接开除.
Let me worry about that.
让我来担心这些吧.
No, teacher, no!
不, 老师, 不!
This moment could change your life for ever.
这个时刻能够改变你的一生.
You might not get a chance like this again, Carlos.
卡洛斯, 你可能不会再有这样的机会了.
If something happens to you, teacher, I'll never forgive myself.
老师, 如果你出点啥事, 我永远不会原谅我自己.
If you don't use that talent, I'll never forgive myself.
如果你浪费了这份才华, 我才没法原谅我自己呢.
Teacher. I'm scared.
老师, 我很害怕.
Carlos...
卡洛斯...
Dancers dance,
舞者只会跳舞,
but artists take risks.
但艺术家愿意承担风险.
Feel like I have the whole of Cuba on my back, teacher.
老师, 我觉得好像整个古巴都压在了我的背上.
I don't want to let her down.
我不想让她失望.
You have the right to fail, that's how you learn.
你可以失败, 失败是学习的一种方法.
It's a great achievement to have been accepted, enjoy it, darling.
能被认可是很大的成就, 享受它吧, 亲爱的.
Londres
伦敦
Welcome! Colleague. How's your trip?
欢迎你, 新同事! 旅途顺利吗?
Nice to meet you!
很高兴认识你.
Guys, this is your new colleague.
伙计们, 这位是你们的新同事.
Leave me alone.
别理我.
We found her naked screaming in the street.
我们发现她赤身裸体在街上尖叫.
They mentioned schizophrenia.
他们说是精神分裂症.
Havana, more than three decades after the revolution,
哈瓦那, 革命后三十多年,
An island nation 90 miles off the coast of Florida.
距离佛罗里达海岸九十英里的岛国
A nation on the verge of economic collapse.
一个正处在经济崩溃边缘的国度.
We will have to instruct the Border Guards
我们不得不指示边防警察
not to block the exit
不要拦截那些
to crafts wanting to travel to the USA.
要去美国的筏子.
The shelters of food ration are empty.
粮仓已经空了.
And families are forced to carefully plan their meals base on what the goverment gives them
各家庭被迫根据政府分配和在黑市能够买到的东西
and what they can buy on the black market.
小心翼翼地安排餐食.
This is a world where people are hungry for the essentials of life.
这是一个生活必需品极度匮乏人民普遍挨饿的世界.
Nowhere are the needs more apparents within the poorest quarters of Havana.
没有哪个地方比哈瓦那的贫民区还惨.
Go ahead, seat the girl first. The girl goes first.
继续, 让那女孩先上, 女孩优先.
I have nothing to feed my kids with. I have to feed them.
我没有食物可以给我的孩子们吃, 我得喂养他们.
How many perished on the crossing, nobody knows.
没有人知道有多少人死于海上横渡.
Thank you.
谢谢.
My friend, can you give me a few coins?
朋友, 能给我点零钱吗?
Kid, do you not remember me? I'm Yuli!
小子, 不认得我了? 我是尤利!
It's me, Yuli.
是我, 尤利.
Yuli!
尤利!
Look, everybody, it's Yuli!
大家快看, 是尤利!
Ah, my son!
啊, 我的儿子!
Ah, Mami. How are you?
妈咪. 你好吗?
Ah, my child!
啊, 我的孩子!
How I've missed you, Mami.
我太想你了, 妈咪.
Let me see you... So handsome.
让我看看你...这么帅了.
How's Berta?
贝尔达好吗?
Berta is better, love.
贝尔达很好, 亲爱的.
Tomorrow we'll see her in hospital.
明天我们去医院看她.
Darling!
亲爱的!
Look at him.
看看他.
Is it true it's always raining?
听说那总是下雨, 真的吗?
Almost.
是的.
But the worst is the cold and damp.
但最糟糕的是寒冷和潮湿.
So how's your foot, Yuli?
你的脚怎么样了, 尤利?
They gave you stitches?
你做了手术?
They removed a bone splinter. Seven stitches.
他们取出了一块骨头碎片, 缝了七针.
It hurt like hell...
疼死我了...
That's nothing. In military service I fucked my ankle... Look.
这没啥. 我当兵时也伤到过脚踝...看.
As far as I know, you are not a ballet dancer, is that right?
据我所知, 你现在不是芭蕾舞者, 对吗?
How did it happen?
怎么拐到的?
One day during a rehearsal...
有一天在排练的时候...
I was a bit homesick, feeling down...
我有点想家了, 情绪低落...
Thinking about you all...
想到你们所有人...
I lost concentration and landed badly.
注意力不集中, 着地时没踩稳.
"Feeling down".
"情绪低落".
- Papi... - Great...
- 老爸... - 好吧...
- Enough. - "Down".
- 够了. - "低落".
Please, he's just landed.
求你了, 他才刚下飞机.
Moaning, moaning... Missing this, missing that...
抱怨, 抱怨...想念这个, 想念那个...
Papi, what's wrong?
老爸, 你啥毛病?
Too wet, too cold, too dark... Fuck me!
太湿, 太冷, 太黑...玩我哪!
Pedro!
佩德罗!
Risking your whole career for nostalgic bullshit!
为了所谓的乡愁赔上你的职业生涯, 狗屁!
I told you to forget about us!
我告诉过你忘记我们!
All you care about is this fucking pigsty!
你就只会关心这该死的猪圈!
Sometimes I wonder if you deserve your God-given talent!
有时我都怀疑你是不是对得起上帝给你的这份天赋!
Talent!
天赋!
Fucking talent dragged me from home age 1 1!
该死的天赋11岁就把我从家里拖了出去!
Against my will.
违背我的意愿.
And so you know, I don't care if I ever dance again! I hate it!
你知道吗, 我根本就不在乎能不能再跳舞! 我恨舞蹈!
Hate it!
我恨它!
I lost my life to fucking ballet!
因为这该死的芭蕾我失去了生活!
Did you ever ask yourself what makes me happy? Me! Eh?
你是否关心过什么能让我幸福? 我! 啊?
- Has that ever passed through your brain? - Happiness? What the fuck is happiness?
- 你究竟想过没? - 幸福? 什么是该死的幸福?
To be with my family, with Mami, with you,
跟我的家人在一起, 跟妈咪在一起, 跟你在一起.
taking care of my sisters...
照顾我的姐姐...
To feel needed.
被需要的感觉.
An ordinary life.
正常的生活.
A family, a home.
一个家庭, 一个家.
Dance is your home.
舞蹈就是你的家.
- Art is your home. - You stole my childhood.
- 艺术就是你的家. - 你偷走了我的童年.
How sweet. Sentimental hokum
好动人啊. 都是些伤感的废话.
for the feeble minded! You've learned fuck all.
意志薄弱! 都学了些什么垃圾.
Papi, sometimes I hate you...
老爸, 有时我恨你...
- What are you saying? - I hate you, that's the truth.
- 你说什么? - 我恨你, 这是真的.
Well, you listen to me.
好吧, 你听着,
I prefer hate to the very last day of your life,
我宁可你恨我一辈子,
instead of your soppy bullshit, bonehead.
也不愿意你这样多愁善感, 笨蛋.
Fuck off!
滚开!
What?
啥?
Be careful... or I'll split you in two.
小心点...不然我劈了你.
Careful, Yuli, careful.
你给我小心点, 尤利, 小心点.
General Major Smedley D. Butler  US Marine Corps 1881-1940
史沫特莱·巴特勒少将 美国海军陆战队 1881-1940
Smedley, Smedley,My name, Smedley
史沫特莱, 史沫特莱, 我的名字是史沫特莱
Smedley D. Butler, Smedley D. Butler
史沫特莱·D·巴特勒, 史沫特莱·D·巴特勒
General Smedley D. Butler
史沫特莱·D·巴特勒将军
High class muscle man, for Big Business, Big Business, for Wall Street, for Bankers, for Wall Street.
大企业, 华尔街, 银行家的高级打手
May Mexico save her American Standard Oil, save her American Oil. Save!
愿墨西哥拯救美国标准石油公司!
May, hey, Cuba, Cuba, Cuba, a decent place for National City Bank.
愿古巴成为国家城市银行投资的好地方.
Bankers, Bankers, National City Bankers.
银行家, 银行家, 国家城市银行的银行家.
Racketeer, Gangster, Rat, Central America for Wall Street! Wall Street!
诈骗犯, 黑帮, 硕鼠, 华尔街的中美洲! 华尔街的!
Grant Nicaragua for Banking Houses, Banking Houses, Banking Houses.
把尼加拉瓜授予大银行, 大银行, 大银行.
Racketeer, Bodyguard, Sucker, Gangster, Racketeer.
诈骗犯, 保镖, 恶棍, 黑帮, 诈骗犯.
IR Chan alcohol, three districts for him, three continents for me.
陈博士的酒, 三个区给他, 三个洲给我.
Racketeer, Gangster.
诈骗犯, 黑帮.
Sucker, US military sucker.
恶棍, 美国军方的恶棍.
My worlds, my life.
我的世界, 我的生活.
General Smedley D. Butler, Smedley, Smedley
史沫特莱·D·巴特勒将军, 史沫特莱, 史沫特莱
Smedley
史沫特莱
Right, folks, I've got some notes for you.
好吧, 伙计们, 有几个地方要注意.
What's this, Carlos? Another of your inventions?
这是什么, 卡洛斯? 你的又一项发明?
What inventions?
什么发明?
Smedley existed, and those are his very words.
有史沫特莱这个人, 这些是他的原话.
Sorry, Carlos, I'm trying to think,
对不起, 卡洛斯, 我想弄明白.
but I don't see what it has to do with your life.
但我没看出来这跟你的生活有什么关系.
Good, you keep thinking and I'll keep rehearsing.
好的, 你继续想, 我接着排演.
Let's move on. Julio, this time it was spectacular.
我们继续. 胡里奥, 这次很不错.
Don't stop, you dickhead. Go on!
别停, 蠢货. 继续开!
- Listen to me. Ignore them. Listen to me. - Stop, stop.
- 听我的, 别理他. 听我的. - 停车, 停车.
Where are your papers?
你的证件呢?
Opito, the glove compartment, grab the papers.
奥比多, 帮我把手套箱里的证件拿出来.
I won't give these fuckers a single penny.
我不想给这些混蛋一个子儿.
I'm not giving them a penny... Going to give them some bars of soap.
不是要给他们钱...给他们几条香皂就好.
I'd give them fuck all.
是我的话就都给他们.
Opito, I've got more at home, give me the soap.
奥比多, 我家里还有很多, 把香皂给我.
- Good evening. - Good evening.
- 晚上好. -晚上好.
Just a moment.
等会.
- Good evening, good evening. - Can I go in or not?
- 晚上好, 晚上好. - 你到底让不让我进去?
Good evening.
晚上好.
- It's full to capacity. - Where are these people going to?
- 客满了. - 那这些人是去哪?
Shut for us, not for them.
把我们关在外面, 而不是他们.
Who owns the country?
谁是这个国家的主人?
Cubans, or these fucking tourists?
古巴人, 还是这些该死的游客?
Look, son, keep out of trouble.
孩子, 别惹麻烦.
- Hands off me! Don't touch me! - Mind yourself.
- 放开我! 别碰我! - 当心点.
- Please, leave now. - Don't touch me!
- 请你离开. - 别碰我.
We're going in.
我们要进去.
- Cool it, boys. - Opito, easy, one second.
- 冷静点, 孩子. -奥比多, 别生气, 等一下.
Tell me, what do you want?
告诉我, 你需要什么?
Listen, man, damn, we're brothers, or not?
听着, 大哥, 我们是兄弟, 对吧?
We are... So what?
我们是...那又怎么样?
Listen, all we want to do is kick back,
听着, 我们就想放松一下.
relax a little in the hotel... Give us a break, eh?
在酒店里放松一点...给我们点方便, 好吗?
Maybe this will help...
这能有点帮助...
What is this?
这是什么?
Just a little something to keep you going...
一点小意思...
Are you trying to bribe a state functionary?
你是打算贿赂国家工作人员吗?
Not a bribe, just a little help.
不是贿赂, 就是一点小意思.
Piss off to Miami!
滚回迈阿密去!
What a prick! And these guys here? Eh?
鸟人! 为什么这些人在这里, 啊?
And this low-life who came to screw our youngsters, fuck our children?
为什么让这些下流的家伙到这里来欺负我们的小姑娘?
And you treat them like lords! You're a cheap scumbag!
你把他们当上帝一样对待! 你就是个下贱的人渣!
Let's go.
我们走.
After you've been away so long, you're not from here, nor from there...
你离开了这么久, 既不算古巴人, 也不算外国人...
Well...
那...
How long are you going to stay?
你打算在这待多久?
Do you know what really gets me?
你知道是什么真正触动了我?
Kids begging in the street, from me, as if I were a stranger.
小孩在街上向我乞讨, 就好象我是个陌生人.
I must be the only Cuban who wants to stay here.
我可能是唯一一个想留在这里的古巴人了.
Everybody I speak to wants to leave.
所有跟我聊过的人都想离开.
Opito and Ramon are building a raft to get out.
奥比多和拉蒙在造个阀子想要离开.
Have they gone mad?
他们是疯了吗?
Brother, you're not chancing it.
兄弟, 你没有机会的.
- Don't preach to me, no sermons... - No fucking way, no, brother, no way.
- 别跟我说教, 别来教训我... - 不行, 兄弟, 真的不行.
Don't preach to me.
别跟我说教.
Easy to preach in your fancy cloths, with your cash, you can travel...
你穿着华丽的衣服, 手握现金, 想飞去哪就飞去哪, 当然有资格说教...
Totally mad! What the fuck's going on? Are you crazy?
全疯了! 到底是怎么回事? 你疯了吧?
It's no bed of roses outside Cuba...
离开古巴并不意味着就有铺满玫瑰的床在等你...
Isn't?
是吗?
If you don't have money or contacts, they treat you like shit, a nobody.
如果你没有钱也没有关系, 他们对待你就像狗屎一样, 你什么也不是.
If you get ill, you'll drop dead, nobody bothers...
如果你病了, 就被扔着等死, 没人会在乎你...
And here?
那这里呢?
And here, Yuli?
这里呢, 尤利?
It's a shithole, brother!
这里就是个粪坑, 兄弟!
You have choices, you can live from your work, as it should be.
你有得选. 你有工作, 好像天生就该这样.
Not me.
我不是.
I work like a dog day and night,
我像只狗一样从早干到晚.
up and down on my taxi-bike... My family are starving.
不停地蹬着我的三轮车... 我的家人在挨饿.
I leave home every morning and I don't know
每天早上我离开家, 我都不知道
if I'll be able to bring them back something to eat...
我能不能给他们带回来点吃的...
But there's got to be another way, brother.
一定会有其他办法的, 兄弟.
What other ways? Tell me?
什么办法? 你告诉我?
Every time I see the leaders of this fucking mess on TV,
每次我看到电视上那些
fattening themselves like pigs...
脑满肠肥猪一样的领导人...
and me, like a prick up and down on my taxi bike. Every day.
而我, 却像个鸟人一样每天蹬着三轮.
So what other way?
你告诉我还有什么出路?
The only thing I have in the whole world to gamble with...
这个世界上唯一我可以拿出来赌的,
The only thing I can count on, that's really mine,
唯一我所能指望, 真正属于我的,
is my life.
就是我的命了.
Give me some time, brother, and I'll help you...
给我点时间, 兄弟. 我会帮你...
Leave it, forget all this shit, brother.
别管我了, 忘记这些吧, 兄弟.
Where's that white chick? She's gorgeous.
那个小白妞去哪了? 她还真是动人.
Fucking shithole!
该死的!
Is there no way to have a good time here?
想开心一下都不行吗?
No more lights... Once again...
没电了...又没电了...
You don't answer my calls.
你没接我的电话.
And you're fat.
还胖了.
Thank you.
谢谢你.
Your father has been calling me.
你父亲打电话给我.
You've broken his heart.
你伤透了他的心.
He's got a heart?
他有心吗?
Ah, teacher... I've got my life back.
老师...我找回了我的生活.
I'm fine.
我很好.
Yes, so I see.
嗯, 我看出来了.
Are you not ashamed to throw it all away?
你放弃了这一切你不觉得羞愧吗?
Teacher, I've enjoyed myself more in these last few months
老师, 我觉得我过去这几个月比我这一生
than in my whole life! That's it!
过得都好! 就是这样!
And when the money runs out?
钱花完了呢?
Look, even if I wanted to,
看, 即使我愿意,
which I don't,
事实上我不愿意,
I don't know if my ankle will take it.
我也不知道我的脚踝能不能撑得住.
- You won't know till you try. - Teacher, it's over!
- 你不试试怎么能知道呢. - 老师, 都结束了!
I've given ballet all I've got. It's done!
我为芭蕾奉献了一切, 都结束了!
And Houston Ballet?
那休士顿芭蕾舞团如何?
The United States?
美国?
You know they won't give me permission here to work there.
你知道他们不会允许我去美国工作的.
Maybe you're right...
也许你是对的...
Teacher, who wants me there?
老师, 谁要我去的?
You said your ankle wouldn't take it?
你说你的脚踝撑不住的?
Damn it, tell me!
该死的, 告诉我!
A good man.
一个好人.
An excellent choreographer and director.
一个优秀的编舞和导演.
I want to see you for rehearsal tomorrow morning at the studio.
我要看到你明天出现在工作室参加排练.
And it's not just about you.
这不仅仅是你一个人的事情.
Here we go again, the whole of Cuba on my back.
又来了, 我背负着整个古巴的希望.
Listen, boy, a little consideration for others,
听着, 孩子, 考虑下其他人,
we have given you everything, for nothing in return!
我们给了你一切, 不求回报!
Shit! Sometimes I want to knock your head off!
该死的! 我有时真想把你的脑袋敲下来!
What a brute you are!
你这个畜生!
And if I can't?
如果我不行呢?
If I'm not good enough?
如果我不够好呢?
Listen, Carlos...
听着, 卡洛斯...
Sometimes in life things don't work out as we hope.
人生有时未必尽如人意.
All you can do, son, is work hard like you always have done.
你所能做的, 唯有像以前那样努力前行.
I'll see you in the studio tomorrow morning.
明早工作室见.
The Director will receive you in a moment.
导演一会就会接见你.
HEAD OF THE NATIONAL CUBAN BALLET
古巴国家芭蕾舞团总监
Two.
二
One,
一
and two.
二.
To the bar.
转向栏杆.
Five, six,
五, 六.
seven, ready, eight.
七, 准备, 八.
And one.
再来, 一.
Hey, kid, come here.
嘿, 小家伙, 过来.
Are you Carlos Acosta?
你是不是卡洛斯阿科斯塔?
Yes.
是的.
I saw you on the TV.
我在电视上见过你.
That's why I'm here.
你是我来这里的原因.
Have you come to give a class?
你是来给我们上课的吗?
No, kid.
不是.
He's off to the big league.
他已经不是高手了.
OK, to your class.
好了, 去上课吧.
No skiving and work!
不逃课就行!
Silence, please.
请安静.
Papi, if she doesn't give me permission, I won't go.
老爸, 如果她不给我许可, 我就不去.
- Yuli... - No, Papi, no.
- 尤利... -不, 老爸, 不.
If she doesn't give me permission, I won't be allowed back home.
如果她不收我, 我也没法回家.
That would kill me, Papi.
那会要了我的命.
HOUSTON BALLET PROUDLY PRESENTS CARLOS ACOSTA
休斯顿芭蕾舞团隆重推荐 -- 卡洛斯·阿科斯塔
The Royal Ballet presents Principal  Dancer Carlos Acosta
皇家芭蕾舞团首席舞者 -- 卡洛斯·阿科斯塔
THE FIRST BLACK ROMEO IN THE ROYAL BALLET, MY SON YULI
皇家芭蕾舞团首位黑人罗密欧, 我的儿子尤利
Teacher...
老师...
Thanks for coming.
谢谢你能来.
I came to wish you luck.
我来祝你好运.
Ah, teacher, like always. Like always.
老师, 你总是这么说.
All the tickets sold out, half of Havana will be here tomorrow.
票都卖光了, 明天半个哈瓦那都会来看.
Just wish your Papi could have been here.
真希望你老爸能来这里.
Remember him in Soho?
还记得他在SOHO的时候吗?
He was so proud of you.
他太为你骄傲了.
There are three secrets of why we are here today in London.
今天我们能够在伦敦相聚是因为三个秘密.
First, this lady, and all the rice and beans she gave him as a boy.
首先是这位女士, 以及在孩提时代她所给他的哺育.
Second,
第二,
his talent,
他的才华,
which he inherited from me.
他从我这里继承的才华.
And third, Chery, and the Cuban School of ballet.
第三, 切莉, 以及古巴芭蕾舞学校.
For a black kid like him,
他这样的黑人小孩,
son of a black lorry driver like me, grandson of a slave,
黑人货车司机的儿子, 奴隶的后代,
he would have survived the roaring fires of hell
进入其他任何一所芭蕾舞学校前,
before getting into ballet school anywhere else.
都能够经受得住地狱烈火般的考验.
My son,
我的儿子,
I have a confession to make.
我要忏悔.
I know that I made you suffer, so much.
我知道我让你受了很多苦.
After years of sacrifice,
经过多年的付出,
today you are an artist, you followed your star.
今天你成为一个艺术家, 你遵循了你的星路.
Your friends here tell me
你这边的朋友告诉我,
that when you retire from dance they want you to stay here.
他们希望你退休后能留在这里.
London will be your home,
伦敦会是你的家园.
your base to conquer the world.
是你征服世界的基石.
The happiest day of my life was the day you were born.
我一生中最开心的日子是你出生的那一天.
Let's toast.
干杯.
Thank you everyone, especially my child Yuli,
谢谢你们, 尤其是我的儿子, 尤利,
named after a warrior, son of Ogun.
勇士之名, 奥岗之子.
YOUR KIDS WILL NOT FORGET YOU
您的孩子永生铭记
Thank you, Papi.
谢谢你, 爸爸.
But you were wrong.
但你说错了,
London is not my home.
伦敦不是我的家.
I am from here.
我来自这里.
I've founded my company here, and one day I'll open up that old school.
我在这里创立了我的公司, 终有一天我将重开那所老学校.
I can only give, what I am.
我只能奉献我自己.
I am your son,
我是你的儿子.
son of Pedro Acosta, the lorry driver Pedro Acosta.
佩德罗阿科斯塔的儿子, 货车司机佩德罗阿科斯塔的儿子.
Son of Ogun,
奥岗之子.
that's me, who I am.
这就是我, 我之所以为我.